So much slop, so little time.
This is Higher Ed Hot
Takes, and I'm Joel Goodman.
As a web designer and marketer,
I've seen it all and unfortunately
it all looks the same.
But you've heard this though, right?
I've been in the higher ed web marketing
game since 2009, and then as now we were
talking about how everyone's website
looks the same or how every institution
has some version of the same tagline.
One of my favorite videos is of my good
friend Jeff Stevens doing a dramatic
reading of dozens of university taglines
to underscore how similar they all are.
So what happens now that we
have generative AI and LLMs?
A lot of us have been integrating chat
GPT into our work, having it draft emails
or website content or news stories.
And that's not necessarily bad if you
have talented writers and editors who
go through and revise those drafts.
But I suspect that not many
of us do, or not many of us
wanna wait around for an edit.
And when budget pressures come around, as
they always do in higher ed, we turn to
cutting staff and underfunding marketing.
Especially now with the promise
of automation through ai.
Why can't we just replace
that writer with chat GPT?
It seems good enough.
Or how about decreasing your
frontline admission staff because
you can replace them with a chat bot.
Even creepier, replace them with
multimodal AI that synthesizes
voices and can talk on the phone.
That stuff creeps me out.
The hitch is that the stuff that we
have right now is not actually ai.
It's machine learning.
We've had machine learning for 20 to
30 years available to us in higher
ed and plenty more accessible ML
tools have been in our toolbox for
the past 10 years or so already.
It's a fact that generative ai, all
of which are trained on the same
core data, can't actually understand
anything because they don't think.
LLMs are predictive algorithms.
They guess what word goes
next to another word.
I haven't seen any proof that it
knows how to differentiate, say,
between Wheaton College and Illinois
and Wheaton College in Massachusetts.
At least not to a degree that ensures
you're not giving prospective students
incorrect information or information
that contradicts your values and brand.
LLMs are at a minimum, a
decade away from anything like
real thought and interaction.
Right now.
Their responses are purely predictive,
and while they might trick you into
believing they know things at times,
we've all experienced the hallucinations.
It's giving too much credit to say they
make mistakes, because these algorithms
have no actual thought or knowledge.
They don't make mistakes.
They just select inaccurate
information to serve up.
Like, I just think there are way too many
questions around the ethics of that for us
to blindly be pouring cash into new tech.
But this comes down to an extremely
nihilistic outlook on society.
A lot of the uses for AI being sold
to us across every sector are just
cynicism wrapped up in a sales pitch.
When you outsource your hiring
to an LLM, what sort of respect
are you showing your applicants?
How would you feel if you found out your
new boss didn't value your expertise
enough to write an acceptance letter?
When putting an AI powered voice
bot between your admission staff
and prospective students, do you
feel you're showing real care?
These are the things
that keep me up at night.
Because we're losing authenticity
and we're losing connection,
and we're taking humanity out
of inherently human experiences.
And when you take the humanity out of
the connection with your prospective
students, you lose the only edge you have.
There aren't that many differentiators
in the marketing that higher ed does.
So that when you lose that core
one, your people and your culture
and the ethos behind what you
do and give it to an algorithm
trained on generic slop, you lose.
And so do your prospects.
Your people are the one selling
proposition that you have
over any other institution.
If you're shoveling your prospective
students off to talk to a robot,
essentially there's a question about how
much you care about them and the process.
How much do you really trust a
large language model or a generative
model to know your brand and to
accurately express your values?
I'm not saying this level of disrespect
is intentional because most of
us in higher ed are good people.
But the level of disrespect that's born
out of a lack of serious consideration
to these things is noticeable.
If the quality of your content declines
because you didn't care enough to put
an actual talented person on the job,
you're disrespecting your audiences.
When your Gen AI images start looking
like everyone else's, you're gonna lose
market share and brand standing while
infringing on the work of real artists.
Slop begets slop.
And a resurgence of
craft is the only remedy.
The web is now filled with AI
generated slop, and the race to
hegemonic mediocrity is full sprint.
Higher ed already has a serious trust
issue, and that's only going to get
worse if we don't remember that humanity
is at the heart of the work that we do.
Look, LLMs have real uses and those
are largely the same as what we've been
using machine learning for for years.
So think a bit broader.
Generative AI, the stuff ChatGPT, Claude
and Mid Journey do is the lowest common
denominator and the easiest thing to sell.
It's surface level stuff and
honestly the stuff a real person
should be doing in production.
You should be using LLMs to support
your craft and not replace it.
That's the lesson here.
Use them for research or data analysis.
Use them for finding
patterns or connecting your
different databases together.
Use them to manage data integrity or
maybe like keep your notes organized,
but don't outsource your human touch.
The world doesn't need more slop.
You're better than that.
Thanks for listening.
If you want to connect, find me Joel
Goodman on Blue Sky and LinkedIn.